Collection of Confederate State of America Materials MS191
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Collection of Confederate State of America Materials
1861 -- 1865
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
MS191
1.96 Linear Feet 2 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series.
Custodial History
These proclamations were found in the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives in 2011; the Ryder collection was cataloged as part of the WPA in 1939/1940 but in later decades the catalog ( A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of the Confederate Archives at Tufts College 1940) was forgotten and library staff added other materials to the Ryder collection, usually items from the South, from the 18th and 19th century and around the time of the Civil War.
Because the proclamations were not part of the original Ryder collection, items were removed and a separate, 'artificial' collection was created.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes materials documenting the political and economic activities of the Confederate States of America during the Civil War. The collection includes bills and amendments; bonds; correspondence; forms; notes; reports; speeches; a list of members of the Confederate States of America House of Representatives; Confederate States of America policy regarding the employment of African American troops; a blank muster roll; and a ledger listing legislative acts and joint resolutions passed by the Congress of the Confederate States. Forms document the desertion of Jefferson Davis (former president of the Confederate States of America), John C. Breckenridge (former Confederate secretary of war), and George Alfred Trenholm (prominent politician and Confederate secretary of treasury), on April 16, 1865. There are also 'Oath and Parole' forms for Davis and Trenholm, of the same date. Reports include a report of the attorney general and the minority report of the Special Committee to investigate the affairs of the navy department.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The Confederate States of America was a collection of eleven Southern states which formed a government when they seceded from the Union in 1860-1861. The government was led by Jefferson Davis, and lasted until the spring of 1865. Though the Confederacy carried on a major war, it ultimately was never recognized as a sovereign nation, and was disbanded after its defeat in the Civil War.
Prior to the outbreak of the war, the South felt their economy and traditions threatened by rising abolitionist sentiment in the North. With the election of Abraham Lincoln, seven states initially seceded from the Union: Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, South Carolina, and Texas. After the first shots of the Civil War were fired at Fort Sumter, Arkansas, North Carolina, Tennessee, and Virginia additionally joined the Confederacy. Headed by President Jefferson Davis, the Confederacy created its own constitution, modeled after the U.S. Constitution.
The principal issue of the Confederacy was raising and equipping an army to fight Union forces. Though bolstered by initial victories in 1861 and 1862, the army was defeated in battles at Gettysburg and Vicksburg, which shattered the illusion of the supremacy of their army. General Robert E. Lee and General Joseph E. Johnston were able to fend off the Northern armies in the North and West for a time, but ultimately were worn down by dwindling manpower and stronger Union armies. After the surrender of Robert E. Lee on April 9th, 1865, Confederate generals in the South subsequently surrendered or disbanded their armies. The Confederacy ceased to exist with the end of the Civil War, and each state was readmitted to the Union in the Reconstruction Era, after individually ratifying the 13th Amendment to the Constitution.
Confederate States of America; Desertion; Oath of loyalty; Bills; Civil War; Soldiers, Black
- Confederate States of America material, 1861 -- 1865; MS191.001; 0.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes Office of Provost Marshall oath and parole forms including those for Jefferson Davis (CS president) and Breckenridge (CS Secretary of War), Confederate Congress printed matter, confederate envelopes, Confederate States of America treasury forms [empty], bound ledger listing acts passed by Confederate Army and joint resolutions.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - United States Office of Provost Marshal desertion and 'Oath and Parole' forms, 1865; MS191.001.001.00001 (Box Shared 14)
    Forms documenting the desertion of Jefferson Davis (former president of CS government) and John C. Breckenridge (former CS secretary of war) on April 16 1865 as well as the 'Oath and Parole' form for Jeff Davis, same date. Also included the desertion documentation and 'Oath and Paole' form for George Alfred Trenholm (prominent politician and secretary of treasury) dating from April 16th 1865.
  - Confederate Congress printed matter, 1864 -- 1865; MS191.001.001.00002 (Box Shared 14)
    Printed matter re acts, resolutions, amendments, communications, report of the attorney general, policy of employing negro troops, address of congress to the people of the Confederate States, minority report of the Special Committee to investigate the affairs of the navy department, and a list of members of the House of Representatives, of the Second Congress.
  - List of bonds sold for Confederate States, 1863; MS191.001.001.00003 (Box Shared 14)
    List of bonds, with numbers and amounts of certificates, sold for account of the Confederate States (of America) to Thomas N. Welch, Dr. R. E. Haskins, James Hawhop [?], and Capt. W. B. Edmonds; signed R. H. Maury & Co by Smith.
  - Acknowledgements of letters received by T. Sanford [illegible addition] written to E. C. Elmore (treasurer of CS), 1864; MS191.001.001.00004 (Box Shared 14)
    Two acknowledgements of letters received by T. Sanford [illegible addition] written to E. C. Elmore from August 12 an 13th 1864.
  - Army Muster Roll, Confederate States of America (empty), 1861 -- 1865; MS191.001.001.00005 (Box Shared 5)
    Dated 186 [empty space].
  - Form for drafts drawn up, Treasurer's Office, Confederate States of America (empty), 1861 -- 1865; MS191.001.001.00006 (Box Shared 14)
    Dated 186 [empty space]. Empty forms with printed signature by E. C. Elmore, Treasurer C. S.
  - Envelope, State Department, Confederate States of America (empty), 1861 -- 1865; MS191.001.001.00007 (Box Shared 14)
  - Bound ledger listing acts and joint resolutions passed by the Congress of the Confederate States, 1862 -- 1865; MS191.001.001.00008 (Box Shared 5)
    Chronological listing, each listing numbered consecutively: front half of ledger lists acts; joint resolutions are listed starting from the back of the ledger. Several handwritings.
  - Handwritten bills of the Congress of the Confederate States of America, 1862 -- 1865; MS191.001.001.00009 (Box Shared 5)
    Very fragile. Many bills written by Robert R. Dixon, clerk, and A. R. Lamar, clerk; many signed by James H Nash, secretary of the Senate. Dates of bills range from Feb 15 1862 to Feb 10th 1865. Also includes e.g. Report of the Committee of Conference Feb 15 1864, handwritten notes, amendments.